相信大家对今年重型猎鹰火箭双助推同步着陆的科幻画面仍然历历在目吧
One of the most impressive sights of recent years was the synchronized landing of the Falcon Heavy boosters
虽然有点小瑕疵，芯级因为点火剂不足无法点火而着陆失败
and although the center core didn't make it back
simply because it didn't have enough ignition fluid to restart all three of a centre cores engines
但任务整体来说还是瑕不掩瑜
the overall mission was a success
但太空叉不是第一个使用该技术的，我们一会会看到历史上其他一些回收的办法
But SpaceX wasn't the first to use this technique and as we will see there are several other ways
to get launch assets back to earth safely without just letting them burn up in the atmosphere
太空叉使用的回收方式是让火箭飞回来
The maneuver which SpaceX use is known as a fly back
这非常依赖氮气调姿发动机、矢量发动机与四个耐热的操控面——格栅舵的完美协调配合
and it requires the perfect coordination of nitrogen cold gas thrusters
gimballed engine burns and the constant adjustment of the four grid fins the heat-resistant control surfaces
来微调猎鹰火箭的飞行轨迹
to fine-tune the Falcons flight path
猎鹰9号一级部分干重超过14吨，却能从太空边缘精确地降落回地面
The first stage of a falcon 9 weighs over 14 tonnes with empty fuel tanks
but it can fly with the greatest of precision to land safely from the edge of space
在高超音速、超过70公里高空的情况下，一级与二级分离
Separating from the second stage at hypersonic velocities and at an altitude of more than 70 kilometers
然后还要穿越情况变幻莫测的高空大气
the Falcon 9 navigates through unpredictable high-altitude atmospheric weather conditions
最后降落在这小小的着陆场上
to land at a precise spot on the Earth's surface
名字翻译取自维基
还有一款能做出类似操作的火箭叫新雪帕德火箭
One other rocket can perform a similar feat and that's new Shepard
杰弗里·贝索斯创办的蓝色起源公司的一款亚轨道火箭
a sub orbital booster built by Jeff Bezos's Blue Origin
新雪帕德火箭箭体上画了一根羽毛，根据贝索斯说，这象征着飞行圆满成功
New Shepard is decorated with the image of a giant feather
which according to Bezos is a symbol of the perfection of flight
2015年11月23日，新雪帕德火箭成为人类首枚飞向太空并成功垂直着陆的火箭
On November 23rd 2015 new Shepard became the first rocket to fly to space and return to make a vertical landing
不到一个月后，2015年12月21日，太空叉的猎鹰9号
Less than a month later on December 21st 2015 SpaceX's Falcon 9
成为了第一个送载荷入轨后成功返回并垂直着陆的火箭
became the first booster to launch a payload to orbit before returning also to land vertically
火箭回收的时代已经悄然开始了，但为什么花了这么久才出现？
The age of reusable rockets had begun but why did it take so long to see it happen?
让火箭着陆固然有很多技术难点要攻克
Landing a rocket presents some serious technical challenges
但其出现如此之晚的根本原因在于轨道发射市场的限制
but the underlying reason for the delay has been the limited market for orbital launches
在以前，火箭制造是由国家或者国际太空组织控制的
In the past the launch industry was controlled by national and international space agencies
即使是资金富裕的政府，也遭不住航天科技研发的烧钱速度
even rich governments have often lacked the resources to fund innovation in space technology
政府投资的火箭原型的多次发射失败，结果通常是项目取消
Repeated launch failures of a government-funded prototype will usually result in the project being canceled
类似事情在20世纪很多优秀的火箭上都有发生
And this is exactly what has happened to many of the 20th century's most
brilliant machines that we often talk about on this channel
杰弗里·贝索斯和马一龙都把钱砸在可回收火箭上了
Jeff Bezos and Elon Musk have invested their personal fortunes into reusable boosters
想以此来降低发射成本，从而激活航天发射市场
with the expectation that in reducing the cost of each launch the market will grow
太空叉和蓝源都在补充那些国际航天组织空出的市场缺口
SpaceX and Blue Origin are filling a niche which has been left open by the national space agencies
但NASA从七十年代就已经在搞可复用航天器了
but reusable space vehicles were a priority for NASA since the 1970s
但他们押错了，航天飞机让一整代的设计止步不前
However once the Space Shuttle was selected America was stuck with a design for a generation
也让他们发现这个能进太空的滑翔机越飞越贵
And their gliding orbiter turned out to be hugely expensive and only grew more inefficient as they aged
铁幕的另一头，毛子那边，暴风雪号航天飞机境遇也差不多
On the other side of the Iron Curtain, there was a similar story the Buran the Soviet space shuttle
最后还是变成了烧钱机器，毛子根本养不起
also became an all-consuming project that the USSR ultimately couldn't afford
但为什么本该是廉价可复用的发射系统，真正用起来非但没省钱反而更贵了呢？
But why did winged space planes do such a poor job
of being what they were supposed to be a reusable affordable launch system
航天飞机的设计上的低效，根本原因是采用了携带超大机翼与发动机入轨的办法
The inefficiency of shuttle design can be traced back to the decision
to carry a large set of wings and engines into orbit
美国的航天飞机重68吨，毛子的暴风雪号是62吨
The American space shuttle weighted 68 tons and the Buran weights 62 tons
都能把不超过30吨的载荷送入近地轨道
and both could deliver a payload of less than 30 tons to low Earth orbit
相当于它们送的任何载荷，都要送总共至少三倍的载荷重量入轨
This meant that any payload delivered by the shuttle or Buran had to be lifted with a
vehicle that tripled the total mass to orbit
这还不算助推器、外挂燃料箱等其他必需的东西
and that was without the booster rockets and the fuel tanks and everything else required to get them there
讽刺的是还要有额外的重量用来装人，还有机翼、绝热瓦
Ironically the extra weight of the crew quarters, wings and heat shielding
这又提升了航天飞机载人的风险
also made the manned shuttle a dangerous way to get into orbit
你把多少吨的载荷加速到入轨，回来就要给多少吨的东西通过大气摩擦减速
For every ton you accelerate to orbital velocity you then need to
decelerate a ton of mass during reentry through friction with the atmosphere
这个过程会产生很多热量，整个载具越重，热量就越多
This process generates a lot of heat and the heavier of a vehicle the more heat creates
两国航天飞机的解决办法都是增大体积，设计中空，增大再入大气时减速面积
The shuttle and Buran dealt with this problem by being large and mostly
hollow at the point of reentry increasing the surface area per ton for atmospheric braking
还有一种“航天飞机”是简单地利用减少入轨质量来降低再入大气时的动压的
But another set of space planes reduced the aerodynamic
pressures of reentry by simply carrying a less mass into orbit
这类小型航天飞机从1960年X-20“动力倍增器”出现在图纸上开始就已经在研发了
Small space planes have been in development since the X-20 "Dyna-Soar" first outlined in 1960
到了21世纪，自动轨道飞行器更轻、功能更多
And 21st century robotic orbital vehicles can do more with less mass
无须载人，免去了生命维持系统，剩下的重量可以放更多更经济的载荷
Without the need for crew quarters or life support they can carry an even more economical payload fraction
美国有两款广为人知的、研发中的自动轨道飞行器
America has two high-profile robotic space planes in development right now
波音的X-37轨道测试载具与内华达山脉公司的逐梦者太空飞机
the Boeing X-37 or orbital test vehicle and the Sierra Nevada corporation's Dream Chaser
它们都是在火箭上垂直起飞，最后再入大气，依靠滑翔在跑道上水平着陆的
Both of these launch vertically and then re-enter the atmosphere and glide to a horizontal runway landing
中国这边也不甘示弱，正在搞的一款太空飞机叫“神龙”
Not to be outdone China is also working on a space plane called the "Shenglong" or divine dragon
神龙在气动上和X-37很像
Shenlong is aerodynamically similar to the X-37
但目前只在2007年中国空军轰-6飞机的肚子下出现过一个用于空投测试的缩尺模型
but has only appeared so far as a scaled-down version for a 2007 drop test from a Chinese Air Force H6 bomber
当小型太空飞机还在缓慢研发的时候
But while small space planes continue in slow development
可复用的助推器早已研究几十年了，有时还增加了长距离飞回的能力
reusable boosters have been studied for decades, sometimes adding a long-range fly back capability
这些想法连猎鹰9号和新雪帕德火箭都无法望其项背
beyond anything possible with a falcon 9 or the new Shepard
第二代能源号项目，就是那个发射暴风雪号的火箭
The second generation of the Energia program, that was the rocket which was to carry the Buran Soviet Space Shuttle
代号是俄语的“飓风”
was code named "Ураган" or "Hurricane"
计划是完全可复用，配有垂直起飞水平降落系统
and was planned as a fully recoverable vertical take off an horizontal landing system
与能源号火箭一样，飓风号将使用捆绑助推器，下面使用四燃烧室RD-170发动机
Like the original Energia rocket Urgan would use strap-on boosters  powered by the four chamber RD-170 engine
RD-170发动机在当年非常先进，设计重复点火十次，测试中成功点火20次
The RD-170 was ahead of its time and designed to ignite up to 10 times and achieving up to 20 relights in tests
苏联工程师敏锐察觉到这一重复启动能力可以让能源号火箭多次发射并重复使用
Soviet engineers realized this relight capability made the Energia boosters suitable for reusability over many launches
当飓风号的助推器分离后，它能伸出一组机翼减速，为再入做准备
When the Urgan's boosters separated from the main stage, it would unfold a set of wings to slow for re-entry
然后是一些机动，最后在跑道上水平着陆
and then maneuver for a horizontal landing on a runway
飓风号的芯级上面也有机翼，长得有点像暴风雪号航天飞机
The center core of the Urgan was also to be fitted with wings a bit like the Buran
Antipodal Bomber, 直译是“地球对面的轰炸机”，学名叫Silbervogel
维基上没翻译，但查到译名是“银鸟亚轨道轰炸机”
它使用和银鸟亚轨道轰炸机相同的技术返回地球
and this was to return to earth using the same technique as the Antipodal Bomber
该技术是由ES这个人在1943年提出的
a design first proposed by Eugen Sänger in 1943
这波操作会让芯级飞出地球大气，直接绕地球一圈
This would have the center core skip off the upper atmosphere around the globe until it
然后返回发射场，像暴风雪号那样在跑道上着陆
returned back to its launch site where it would then land like the Buran itself on a runway
虽然这个操作太窒息了，研发后来也没跟进，但带翼助推器的设计则太有价值了
Although the antipodal design was not followed up, the winged booster design was too good to abandon
使得这个理念在苏联解体后的安加拉火箭的助推器中仍然被多次提出
and it reappeared after the fall of the Soviet Union as proposed booster for the Angara system
这个能飞回来的助推器叫”贝加尔“号，理念和之前的飓风号如出一辙
The fly back booster was called Байкал and was essentially the same concept as the Urgan
上面装有可折叠机翼，还有可吸入空气的航空发动机RD-33用于大气内飞行
fitted with folding wings and an air-breathing RD-33 jet engine for atmospheric flight
从1999年开始德国宇航中心也开始研究过类似的系统“DLR”
A similar system was also studied by the German Aerospace Center the DLR from 1999
来替换阿里安5火箭上的固推
to replace the expendable solid rocket boosters on the Ariane 5 launcher
每一发“可返回液体助推器”（LFFB）装有鸭翼与涡扇发动机
Each liquid fueled fly back booster or LFBB had forward canards small rear wings and a turbofan engine
让助推器拥有和飞机一样的大气内飞行能力
giving the booster all the aerodynamic capabilities of an aircraft
LFBB在取消前只造出来了一些缩尺模型
The LFBB design progressed as far as scale models before being cancelled
显然是设计太大太复杂，没法满足经济性了
apparently because the hardware was becoming too large and complex to justify the economic savings
但欧空局ESA最近投资了空客的可复用一级火箭的研发，来适配未来阿里安6火箭
But ESA has recently funded a new
reusable first stage booster designed at Airbus to work with the upcoming Ariane 6 launcher
项目全称叫“装有船新便宜的发动机的牛逼的可拓展火箭”（ADELINE）
The Advanced Expendable Launcher with Innovative Engine Economy or ADELINE
它使用了一种不常见的气动布局，拥有飞回的能力与达到最优效益的潜力
uses an unusual set of aerodynamic features to potentially achieve the most efficient and capable fly back yet
当一级燃料耗尽后，ADELINE与一级分离并在顶部防护罩的保护下再入大气
Once the first stage fuel is expended ADELINE separates and reenter to the atmosphere
protected from the heat by the shield in the nose
当进入大气比较浓密的部分后
Once in the denser part of the atmosphere the
发动机会利用机翼和一对螺旋桨机动，在跑道上水平着陆
booster uses wings and a pair of propellers to maneuver to a horizontal landing on a runway
螺旋桨比喷气式发动机效率更高
Propellers can achieve even better efficiencies than jet engines
使得飞回来所需油耗会少很多
meaning that even less fuel needs to be reserved for the fly back
现在SpaceX的所作所为，某种程度上迫使全球其他航天企业
Now something which SpaceX is doing is forcing the rest of the launch industry
重新评估他们的不可复用发射系统的效益了
to re-examine their use of non reusable launch systems
几年前俄罗斯宇航局说他们觉得研发可复用火箭完全没用
A few years ago the Russian space agency, Roscosmos said that they didn't see any point in developing reusable rockets
但随着最近SpaceX的壮大与其在航天市场所占份额的提升
But after the recent success of SpaceX and their growing share of a market
俄罗斯宇航局摸着被打肿的脸与快被抢走的饭碗说他们也要搞火箭回收啦
Roscosmos is now say they are actively looking at reusable rockets
“真香”
所以未来应该能看到全球各大航天企业的各种火箭的回收啦
So expect to see a lot more in the way of rockets and boosters flying back to base by themselves
所以你觉得太空叉和蓝源的回收方式如何呢？
So what do you think of SpaceX and Blue origins vision of a reusable future
欢迎在评论区讨论
Let me know what you think in the comments
感谢在Patreon上赞助的朋友，感谢给给虫充电的同学
I would also like to thank all of our patreons for their ongoing support
and you can find out more about that in the link now showing
YouTube频道叫Curious Droid，字幕翻译给虫
And also don't forget to check out some of our other videos too
记得点赞、投币、收藏、分享、关注
So it just remains me to say thanks for watching and please subscribe, thumbs up and share